Finding Aid for Bernard A. Galler Papers 1956-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bernard A. Galler Papers 1956-1996, 1960-1986
Galler, Bernard A.
28.5 linear feet
University of Michigan professor of mathematics, charter member of the department of computer and communication sciences; papers include biographical information; correspondence, 1959-1993; files relating to his participation on various boards and professional organizations; and files pertaining to his University of Michigan research activities and to his participation in university affairs and governance.
0066 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Galler and came to the library in three principal accessions, 1995-1996. Donor no. 8437.
The collection is open for research.
Bernard A. Galler received a B.S. in Mathematics and a Ph.B. in Liberal Arts from the University of Chicago in 1946 and 1947. He earned a M.A. in Mathematics from the University of California in 1949 and a Ph.D. in Mathematics from the University of Chicago in 1955. He joined the University of Michigan Department of Mathematics in 1955 as an instructor; he was promoted to assistant professor in 1959, associate professor in 1962, and professor in 1966.
Galler was a pioneer in the field of computer science, helping to shape this discipline at the University of Michigan. In the early 1960s, he was active in the development of the new Communications Sciences Program, and in 1966, he became associate director of the Computing Center. His association with the center continued through 1991. He became a charter member of the new Department of Computer and Communication Sciences in 1966 and served as its chair from 1973 to 1975. In 1984, Galler was instrumental in negotiating the merger of the CCS department and the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.
Galler also contributed to the University of Michigan's many innovations in the computer field. From 1958 onward, the Computing Center of the University of Michigan was a leader in the development of general-purpose, highly-productive operating systems. In the mid-1950s MIDSAC and MIDAC computers built at the Willow Run Laboratory were among the first computers built and used at universities in the U.S. The MAD (Michigan Algorithm Decoder) translator, created around 1960 and used by the entire campus for a number of years, contained innovative language features which were introduced much later into popular, high-level languages.
Galler also served the wider university community as Associate Dean for Long Range Planning in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts from 1975 to 1979. He served on many university-wide committees and task forces and, in addition, served as undergraduate counselor for the computer science degree program for many years. Very active professionally, Galler was president of the Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) from 1968 to 1970 and was active in the American Federation of Information Processing Societies (AFIPS). He received the AFIPS and ACM Distinguished Services Awards. In 1994, Galler retired from active faculty status after 38 years of service.
The papers of Bernard A. Galler measure 28.87 linear feet and date from 1956 to 1994. The bulk of the papers document the years 1960 to 1986 and concern Galler's high level of involvement in the information processing profession at the University of Michigan, nationally, and internationally. The papers are arranged in five series: Biographical, Chronological Correspondence, Professional and Other Activities, University of Michigan and Audiotapes.
The materials acquired in 2006 (boxes 28-29) were from Galler's office located in the Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI). These materials (1.5 linear foot, 1957-1996) focus mainly on the Software Patent Institute. There were a few files from early years acquired with this accession and they are described as part of the previously established series Chronological Correspondence, Professional and Other Activities and University of Michigan. The exception was the addition of an Audiotape series that contains reel-to-reel tapes of lectures Alan J. Perlis gave in 1959.
Subjects:
American Federation of Information Processing Societies.; Association for Computing Machinery.; Computers--Study and teaching.; Corporation for Research and Educational Networking.; Computer science.; Galler, Bernard A., 1928-; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Computer and Communication Sciences.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences.
- Biographical
  The series, Biographical, consists of one folder containing Galler's vitae and an interview conducted by his wife, Enid Galler, in 1981. The interview records Galler's reflections on the many activities and projects he was involved in the course of his career.
  - Vitae and transcript of oral interview (Box 1)
- Chronological Correspondence 1959-1993
  The Chronological Correspondence series dates from 1959 to 1993, although the bulk of it dates from 1961 to 1987. Measuring five feet, the correspondence reflects Galler's wide range of interests and activities in the information processing profession. Galler corresponded with those in industry and computer scientists at other universities both at a national and international level. Industry correspondents included those at Burroughs and Xerox. Galler's opinion was frequently sought on new products in the industry and for suggestions regarding candidates for positions and awards in academia and industry. His high level of professional involvement is also reflected in this series. Galler served on several external review committees for other universities in the 1970s and 1980s. The correspondence and reports surrounding these reviews offer the researcher glimpses of the status of computer science programs at other universities within the United States. Some of the institutions for which Galler served as a member of an external review committee include: The University of California at Berkeley in 1975, Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1977, the University of New Mexico in 1982, and the University of Pittsburgh in 1986. The series also includes correspondence with students, in some cases long after they left University of Michigan. University of Michigan correspondence is included in this series as well. Correspondents include Robert Kohrflage, Bruce Arden, Anthony Ralston, Philip Dorn, Bob Rosin, and Alan Perlis.
  - 1959-1963, 10 folders (Box 1)
  - 1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1966-1967, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - 1969-1970, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - 1971-1974, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1975-1981, 14 folders (Box 4)
  - 1982-1993, 18 folders (Box 5)
  - 1992-1995, 1 folders (Box 28)
- Professional and Other Activities
  The series Professional and Other Activities is the largest in the collection, measuring 13.5 linear feet, and is divided into several subseries: Board Activities, Consulting, Projects, and Other Activities. This series reflects most clearly the high level of creative participation that Galler had in his profession.
  - Board Activities
    The subseries, Board Activities, 1959 to 1993 (1.75 ft.), documents Galler's involvement either as a member of the board of directors or the advisory board of several companies. The longest periods of involvement are reflected in Data Use and Access Laboratories (DUALabs) and National CSS. Documentation of Galler's involvement with DUALabs dates from 1970 to 1985. DUALabs had a nonprofit mission of providing research, training and database development service for users of publicly available statistics, especially census data. Galler's primary correspondent was John C. Beresford, president. Galler was an active promoter of the company and corresponded with Beresford regarding the company's operations. In addition to correspondence, the DUALabs material includes financial information and board minutes. Beresford resigned from DUALabs in 1982 to establish a for-profit company, DUAL-Comm. Galler was a member of the Board of Directors of National CSS, an information services company, from 1975 to 1979. The records include correspondence, press releases, and board minutes.
    - ArborText 1989 (Box 6)
    - DUALabs 1970-1985, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - National CSS 1975-1983, 9 folders (Box 7)
  - Consulting
    The Consulting subseries documents various consulting activities in which Galler was involved, including acting as an expert witness in legal cases. The work for Booth Newspapers involved designing a computer system for production and business jobs for nine individual newspapers. The project is very well documented through correspondence.
    - Booth Newspaper 1963-1988, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - CalComp 1976-1977 (Box 8)
    - City College of New York 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - General Motors 1971-1977 (Box 8)
    - IBM 1974-1976 (Box 8)
    - Israel 1967-1985, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Socony Mobile Oil Company 1960 (Box 8)
    - Syracuse University 1967-1974 (Box 8)
  - Other Professional Activities
    The subseries titled Other Professional Activities, is the largest within the Professional Activities series and best documents Galler's wide ranging involvement in the profession. One of these profession affiliations was with the American Federation of Information Processing Societies. Galler was heavily involved in the efforts of AFIPS to establish an historical center to enable the profession to document itself. Galler's involvement with the Association for Computing Machinery, particularly his work on the Turing Award Committee underlines the extent of his professional network and his grasp of the profession in terms of contributions made.
    Also included with this subseries is Galler's contributions to the creation of the Corporation for Research and Educational Networking (CREN). Created when the Because It's Time Network (BITNET) and the Computer Science Network (CSNET) merged in October 1989, the mission of CREN was to provide low-cost connection services, and to foster new network technology and applications in support of low-cost connections, for education and research in both the academic and industrial communities. CSNET was a project of the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research under contract to the National Science Foundation; it provided network communications services to organizations engaged in computer-related research, education, and advanced development. Most of its members were in computer science departments and in industry. BITNET served higher education and research facilities. The successful merger of the two was complex, technically and organizationally, and testifies to Galler's leadership and organizational skills.
    Galler served on the Science Council for Applied Mathematics and Computer Science, which was the scientific board of directors for the Institute for Computer Applications in Science and Engineering (ICASE) and the Research Institute for Advanced Computer Science (RIACS). Funded by NASA, through the University Space Research Association, ICASE was established in 1982. It was chartered to carry out state-of-the-art research in computer science and engineering in areas of potential long-term application to NASA programs. Galler also chaired the planning committee for the Center of Excellence in Space Data and Information Science.
    As a member of the Science Committee of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization in 1968, Galler participated in explorations of a software institute. The effort is noteworthy because it represents an early attempt to cooperate internationally on the development of software.
    - Advanced Research Projects Agency 1964-1969 (Box 8)
    - Alcor 1964 (Box 8)
    - American Federation of Information Processing Societies (AFIPS)
      - Correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 8)
      - China Trip 1987 (Box 8)
      - Committee on Electronic Funds Transfer Systems 1968-1979, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Dissemination of Information Committee 1967-1968 (Box 9)
      - History of Computing Committee
        - 1978-1983, 8 folders (Box 9)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 10)
      - Pioneer Day 1986-1987 (Box 10)
      - Publications Committee 1984-1988, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Spring Joint Computer Conference 1963-1964, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Taxonomy Committee 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Twentieth Anniversary 1985-1986 (Box 10)
    - Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)
      - Awards Committee 1977-1978 (Box 11)
      - Committee on the Dissemination of Information 1966-1967 (Box 11)
      - Committee on International Activities 1973-1976 (Box 11)
      - Committee on Member Attitudes to Non-Technical Activities, 1978-79 (Box 11)
      - Committee on Taxonomy of Computer Science and Engineering 1976-1981 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence
        - 1964-1981, 7 folders (Box 11)
      - Council 1966-1967, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Fortieth Anniversary Program 1985-1986 (Box 12)
      - Government Organization Committee 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - National Conference 1964-1967 (Box 12)
      - Nominating Committee 1971-1973 (Box 12)
      - Programming Languages Committee 1965, 1968 (Box 12)
      - Turing Award Committee
        - 1971-1979, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - UM Student Chapter 1965-1967 (Box 13)
    - Award Nominations
      - ACM 1974-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 13)
      - Other 1971-1992 (scattered dates) (Box 13)
    - Ben Gurion University Review Committee 1986-1987 (Box 13)
    - Berg, Herman 1993 (Box 13)
    - Bredt, Thomas 1980, 1986 (Box 13)
    - Charles Babbage Institute/Foundation 1979-1994, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Committee for Alexander Y. Lerner 1976-1981 (Box 13)
    - Committee on Experimental Computer Science (Feldman Committee) 1979 (Box 13)
    - Computer Products Testing Laboratory 1981-1982 (Box 13)
    - Computer Science Board 1974 (Box 13)
    - Conference Board of the Mathematical Sciences 1969 (Box 13)
    - Corporation for Research and Educational Networking (CREN)
      - Computer Science Network (CSNET) Executive Committee Meetings 1984-1989 (Box 14)
      - Network Merger Plans 1988 (Box 14)
      - Board of Trustees
        - 1989-1990, 3 folders (Box 14)
        - 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Correspondence and Reports 1988-1990, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Council for Israel's Economic Development 1969-1970 (Box 15)
    - Crabtree, Robert 1962 (Box 15)
    - EDEBE Workshop 1985-1986 (Box 15)
    - Feng, Tse-Yun 1977 (Box 15)
    - Intelligent Vehicle Highway System Architecture Working Group 1991 (Box 15)
    - Jerusalem Conference on Information Technology (JCIT)
      - 1971 JCIT (Box 15)
      - 1978 JCIT, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 1984 JCIT, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - 1990 JCIT (Box 16)
    - Jet Propulsion Laboratories 1972 (Box 16)
    - MIT Press History Series 1984-1986 (Box 16)
    - Michigan Evaluation Resource Center 1982-1984 (Box 16)
    - Michigan Technology Council 1981-1983 (Box 16)
    - National Academy of Science/National Research Council Division of Mathematical Sciences 1971-1974 (Box 16)
    - National Center for Atmospheric Research Computing Facility Advisory Panel 1972-1974, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - National Council of Teachers of Mathematics 1961-1962 (Box 16)
    - National Research Council
      - Computer Science Planning Group 1975-1980, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Computer Science Technology Board 1977-1979 (Box 17)
    - National Science Foundation
      - Computer Science and Engineering Advisory Panel 1971-1974 (Box 17)
      - Computer Science and Engineering Research Study ("Arden Study") 1974-1981, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - Division of Computing Research (formerly Office of Computing Activities) 1973-1986 (Box 17)
    - North Atlantic Treaty Operation (NATO)
      - International Institute on Computer Science 1968-1969 (Box 17)
      - International Summer School on Computer Programming 1967 (Box 17)
      - Munich Conference 1971-1972 (Box 17)
        (includes black and white photographs)
    - Northwest Computer Association Conference 1962 (Box 17)
    - South America 1972 (Box 17)
    - USA/Japan Seminar 1984-1987, 5 folders (Box 18)
    - UNIVAC I Oral History Conference 1990 (Box 18)
    - Universities Space Research Association
      - Committee for NASA/Langley Computer Science Center 1972 (Box 18)
      - Research Institute for Applications of Computer Science 1982 (Box 18)
      - Science Council 1983-1991, 4 folders (Box 18)
      - Center of Excellence in Space Data and Information Science Planning Committee and Science Council 1985-1987 (Box 18)
    - University of Hawaii Summer Conference 1966 (Box 19)
    - University of Maryland Office Automation Seminar 1982-1983 (Box 19)
    - University of Nijmegen 1971-1972 (Box 19)
    - Wolfston, James 1977-1992, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Projects
    - Barak Project 1990 (Box 19)
    - Computer Analysis of Musical Sounds
      - Correspondence 1976-1983, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Grants and Funding
        - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 19)
        - National Science Foundation (Box 19)
        - Office of Naval Research (Box 19)
      - MUSE Program Code (Box 20)
      - Reports and Papers (Box 20)
    - Computing News Article 1958-1959 (Box 20)
    - Crossword Puzzle Software Project 1987 (Box 20)
    - Dwyer/Galler Project
      - 1956-1969, 3 folders (Box 20)
        (includes General Motors reports)
      - Dwyer Report 1956 (Box 20)
    - Fluid Dynamics Handbook Chapter 1958-1960 (Box 20)
    - Information Utility 1979-1983, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Linear Programming Paper 1958 (Box 20)
    - Perlis Memorial 1991 (Box 20)
    - Piszczalski Projects 1983-1992 (Box 20)
    - Preservation of Microcomputer Software Symposium 1989-1990 (Box 20)
    - Rajlich/Galler Proposal 1984 (Box 20)
    - Software Engineering Institute 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Software Patent Institute 1990-1993, 8 folders (Box 21)
    - U.S. Air Force Programming Systems Evaluation 1962-1963 (Box 21)
    - Visually Impaired Terminals 1982-1984 (Box 22)
    - Voice Recognition System 1979 (Box 22)
    - Wilson/Galler Project 1962 (Box 22)
    - Word Processing Service Proposal 1981 (Box 22)
  - Aerobus 1977 (Box 28)
  - Algol History 1960 (Box 28)
  - OmniText, Business Plan Summary 1971 (Box 28)
  - Papers
    - Criteria for the Design of a Language, not dated (with A.J. Perlis) (Box 28)
    - Generation of Computer Programs by a Computer, (with Robert M. Graham), not dated (Box 28)
  - Publications
    - A 704 Program for the Solution of a Distribution Problem with Few Shippers June 11, 1957 (Box 28)
    - 704 Program for the Solution of a Generalized Distribution Problem, March 1957 (Box 28)
    - The Language of Computers: An Introduction, 1961 (Box 28)
    - Translating the Method of Reduced Matrices to Machine March 1957 (Box 28)
  - Software Patent Institute
    - General Files 1994-1996, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting 1994-1996, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Education Committee 1992-1993 (Box 28)
    - Executive Committee Meeting 1994 (Box 28)
- University of Michigan
  Within the University of Michigan series, Galler's research activities and his participation in university affairs and governance are documented. Of note are the folders on the Computer Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) within the College of Engineering. Started in 1982, CAEN responded to a need for expanded computing power for students and faculty through university-owned machines and unlimited access for students and faculty. These folders include memoranda among the CAEN executive committee, Executive Committee agendas, and other papers. The researcher should also consult the records of the College of Engineering for more information on this subject.
  - Applied Linguistics Program 1985-1986 (Box 22)
  - Center for Information Technology Integration 1986 (Box 22)
  - Coalition for the Analysis of Public Issues 1974 (Box 22)
  - College of Engineering
    - Computer, Information and Control Engineering Program Review 1974-1977 (Box 22)
    - Computer Aided Engineering Network (CAEN) 1983-1988, 10 folders (Box 22)
    - Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Computing Needs 1984-1987 (Box 23)
    - Engineering Design Project 1965 (Box 23)
    - Engineering Summer Conference
      - Correspondence and Other Papers 1966-1974, 3 folders (Box 23)
      - Perlis Lecture Notes 1959 (Box 23)
  - Committee on Access to Academic Records 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Committee on Computer Science and Engineering 1982 (Box 23)
  - Computer Center Search Committee 1976-1977 (Box 23)
  - Computing Center Dedication 1971 (Box 23)
  - Computer Research Laboratory 1982-1984 (Box 23)
  - Computer Registration Involving Student Participation (CRISP)
    - 1971-1973, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Correspondence 1965-1994, 12 folders (Box 24)
  - Department of Computer and Communication Sciences
    - Correspondence 1968-1972, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Honors Council 1981-1982 (Box 25)
  - English Composition Board 1981-1986, 3 folders (Box 25)
  - Governance Activities
    - Building Committee 1973 (Box 25)
    - General 1968-1972 (Box 25)
    - Commission on Role of the Student in Decision-Making 1967-1969 (Box 25)
  - Historical Scientific Equipment 1984-1990 (Box 25)
  - Institute For Science and Technology Committee on Adaptive Systems 1961 (Box 25)
  - Intelligent Vehicle Highway System Project 1988-1991, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Internet 1984-1986 (Box 26)
  - IBM Proposals 1983-1984 (Box 26)
  - Laboratory for Music and Technology 1976-1981, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Literature, Science, and the Arts
    - Executive Committee 1970-1971, 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Internship 1979-1981 (Box 26)
  - MAD (Michigan Aglorithm Decoder)
    - MAD DOGMA 1959 (Box 26)
    - MAD /1 Meetings 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - MAD Definition Facility Paper 1968-1969 (Box 26)
  - MTS/Pioneer High School 1975-1980 (Box 26)
  - Minority students 1969-1970 (Box 26)
    (including 10% black enrollment committee)
  - Sabbaticals
    - University of Amsterdam 1964-1965 (Box 26)
      (Strichting Mathematisch Centrum-worked with Alan Perlis on book on Automatic Programming)
    - University of Newcastle 1973 (Box 26)
    - General 1980-1988 (Box 26)
  - SMILE Language 1967 (Box 26)
  - Teaching
    - Computer Science 181 1986 (Box 27)
    - Communication Sciences 274 1966 (Box 27)
    - CCS 673 1968 (Box 27)
    - History of Programming Languages CS/EECS 498 1992 (Box 27)
      (taught by Jean Sammet)
  - University Committee on Rights of Privacy and Access to Information (UCRPAI) 1976-1980 (Box 27)
    (concerning issue of privacy and need to reveal social security number)
  - Word Processing Coordinating Committee 1979-1982 (Box 27)
  - Engineering Summer Conferences 1971 (Box 28)
  - Teaching
    - CCS673, Winter 1972 (CRISP System development) (Box 28)
    - CCS673, Winter 1975 (Smith II User Manual) (Box 28)
    - Dissertation Committee Correspondence circa 1978-1993 (Box 28)
- Audiotapes 1959-1960 (Box 29)
  - Alan Perlis Lectures, June / July, 1959, reel-to-reel audiotapes (Box 29)
- Video Material